and we are waiting for the Swedish royal
family to arrive and of course uh this
year's laureates
who will take a seat up on the podium
but unlike normal years we'll also have
lawyers from 2020 and 2021 on stage and
here in the audience we have uh their
family but also a prominent guest from
the different price giving institutions
these are the chairs where the Swedish
royal family will be seated and up on
the podium as well then uh laureates
from the last three years 20 20 21 and
22.
in normal year the laureates get to
bring their partner and 14 guests well
that wouldn't work this year so now in
practice they can bring 10 guests
there's about the seating for a little
bit more than 1500 guests here in the
Stockholm Concert Hall
one of the laureates that will receive
his prize this year is actually back
again chemistry Lord Paris sharpless is
here for the second time as a Laureate
we will hear music from the Stockholm
Philharmonic Orchestra and also a
special piece that will Premiere which
is uh to uh
the honor of the laureates of 2020 and
21 who couldn't come here
the music
is the Philharmonic
are
are with this year's conductor Emilia
huving who is one of the most promising
young Finnish conductors and soloist
Hana husar the soprano that we saw in
picture there
the flowers this year do not actually
come from San riemo as they usually do
the Italian city where Alfred Nobel
lived his last years the pandemic messed
up the logistics a bit but the Nobel
Foundation says that contacts with
summary will continue so flowers this
year are imported from the Netherlands I
believe and the decorations have taken
four days to set up by head florist
hillian Magnuson
the behind the Nobel bust we see here we
find Fern
monstera and Ivy
consideration has been given to
sustainability Nature's Greenery
along the sides there is among other
flowers cushion and and Greenery cushion
moss and Scandinavian reindeer lichen
and red cut flowers such as carnations
gloriosa
amaranthus and anthurium
the number of laureates participating in
the Nobel week varies from year to year
we have had some anniversaries like
2001 when the price turned 100
where all laureates who had ever
received the price were invited
excluding the the special anniversary
years 2022 will see the highest ever
number of Nobel Prize laureates
participating in the Nobel week
and everything this will start the
ceremony will start when the Swedish
royal family enters the room here we see
pictures of uh party leaders from the
Swedish political parties and we also
have members of the government and the
Diplomatic Corps uh
attending this prize ceremony
members of Swedish
business community
and more
High
more politicians
sitting here all waiting for the
ceremony to commence
the laureates
will not only receive a diploma which is
a unique work of art created by former
Swedish and Norwegian artists and
calligraphers
the Nobel Prize medals will also be
handed over alongside the diploma
from the hands of the his majesty the
king and then medals are handmade with
careful position in 18 karat recycled
gold
and of course there's a little sum of
money as well that they can walk away
with 10 million Swedish Kroner which is
uh about a million dollars or Euros
roughly
and here we have prints
called Philip and Princess Sofia
first ones from the royal family to
enter the concert hall
so now it shouldn't be more than
a minute or so before the royal family
uh King Cole Gustav and queen Sylvia
enter the room
together with Crown Princess Victoria
and uh
Daniel
[Music]
foreign
the King's Song
and now to the tunes of music by
Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart we will have the
laureates
entering
on stage
[Music]
foreign
[Applause]
[Music]
foreign
physics
[Music]
22 professors
foreign
[Music]
this year's laureates we see the words
from previous years
[Music]
foreign
thank you right
[Music]
right
your Royal highnesses
your majesties your Royal highnesses
esteemed Nobel laureates
ladies and gentlemen
on behalf of the Nobel Foundation it's a
great pleasure for me to welcome you all
to this year's Nobel Prize award
ceremony
in particular I wish to welcome the
Nobel Prize laureates
from 2022 as well as the two previous
years and their families
this year is special
since the coronavirus pandemic prevented
us from holding regular festivities just
to last years we are now all the happier
this year to see the stage filled with
Nobel Prize laureates
this gives us a tremendous opportunity
to celebrate science and culture and we
are very glad to see you all here in
Stockholm
earlier today in Oslo
the prisoner of conscience and human
rights Advocate
from Belarus and the Russian human
rights organization Memorial and the
Ukrainian human rights organization
Center for civil liberties received this
year's Nobel Peace Prize
for many years they have promoted the
right to criticize those in power and to
protect the fundamental rights of
citizens emphasizing the significance of
Civil Society for peace and democracy
in Oslo in Stockholm we need to get
today at a time when freedom is in
Decline globally
when there is war in Europe
even with the Specter of nuclear weapons
with dramatic energy and food crisis
across the world
with glaring discrimination social and
economic inequality
and accelerating climate change which
requires the Urgent scaling up of
solutions
facing this multitude of Crisis and
challenges
the world needs dedicated scientists who
relentlessly seek the truth and push the
boundaries of our knowledge
and the world needs those individuals
and groups which at a great personal
sacrifice challenge authorities in
Pursuit Of Peace democracy and human
rights
the domain price is awarded to
individuals for concrete achievements in
science literature and peace
but with a higher shared purpose their
benefit to humankind
Nobel Prize laureates are part of a
community which has in profound ways
changed the world
they demonstrate the capacity we have as
human beings to shape our own destiny
as such the Nobel Prize it's laureates
and their achievements are a tremendous
source of inspiration and hope which
today is needed more than ever
and the universal ambition to serve the
benefit of human can is also needed more
than ever
this is our guiding star when the Nobel
foundation will generate support from
the ireling passion foundation and the
Knute and Alice Valley by Foundation now
prepares for the future Nobel Center
a house for science culture and dialogue
to be located at Slauson here in
Stockholm
in his will Alfred Nobel is directed
that the prices be awarded to those who
had conferred the greatest benefit to
humankind regardless of nationality
this was Radical and Visionary in the
late 19th century an era marked by
nationalism a phenomenon which sadly is
on the offensive in many countries even
today
but time has proven Alfred nobel's
Vision to be powerful
it is indeed the open exchange between
countries and cultures that promotes
human Progress free science free culture
humanism and internationalism
today we are celebrating the 2022 Nobel
prizes
they are being awarded for scientific
breakthroughs that spans from intricate
and mind-boggling evidence that
particles can be entangled despite being
at a far distance from each other
to elegant solutions to simplify
chemical reactions by click chemistry
facilitating the synthesis of medicines
and allowing the monitoring of
biological processes in living cells
to insights in how to minimize the risks
for financial crisis
Antioch analysis of extinct ominous
which have given us invaluable
information about human evolution
we also celebrate the literature which
uncovers the roots
estrangements and Collective restraints
of personal memory
allow me to close by addressing all the
laureates from 2020 and 2021 absent or
present
I would like to All Join Me Now in
honoring the law rates of 2020 who have
joined us here today
physics Reinhard gansel and Andrea giese
chemistry Emmanuel charpontier and
Jennifer dudna
physiology or medicine
Harvey Alter and Charles Rice
economic Sciences Paul Milgram
and the low rates of 2021
physics Giorgio Parisi
chemistry Benjamin list and David
Macmillan
physiology or medicine David Julius and
Arden pataputyan
literature
[Applause]
and economic Sciences Joshua angerist
and Guido infants
thank you
I am delighted to announce that the
Nobel Foundation has commissioned a
musical piece especially for these
laureates
I invite you all to enjoy the world
premiere of Laos kanticum a song of
Praise by the Swedish composer Andrea
tarode
we thank Professor col Henry kaldin the
chairman of the board of the Nobel
Foundation
[Music]
thank you
foreign
[Music]
right
now
[Music]
foreign
thank you
[Music]
that was a well the premiere of Swedish
composer Andrea taroti's song of Praise
dedicated to the laureates of 2020 and
21.
she could not come here
then due to the pandemic
now it's time for this year's prize
presentation when it comes to the
physics prize
your majesty is your Royal highnesses
esteemed Nobel Prize low rates
ladies and gentlemen this year's Nobel
Prize is dedicated to Quantum Mechanics
Albert Einstein Niels Bohr and Irvin
schradinger all thought about quantum
mechanics in 1935
Einstein challenged quantum mechanics
and argued that although correct it's
not a complete theory he thought there
has to be an underlying structure of
quantum mechanics that had not so far
revealed itself
but Bohr on the other hand he did he
defended the theory and argued that it
was complete
finally schradinger concluded that
entanglement between two particles with
the common past was the characteristic
trait of quantum mechanics
most physicists is cited with boar and
noted Schrodinger's characterization of
entanglement but mostly they were not
that interested they were too busy
applying quantum mechanics to real world
problems both a fundamental character
and for practical applications
several of these fractionaries or
quantum mechanics would eventually
receive the Nobel pricing physics and
many of the things we today take for
granted such as stream television fast
internet mobile phones and a plethora of
a medical diagnostic tools all have the
origins in quantum mechanics indeed the
lower rates are 2020 and 2021 Roger
Penrose Reina again said Andrea guest
Klaus hustleman and Giorgio Parisi are
no exceptions
while the world move on a few physicists
continue to think about the foundation
of quantum mechanics
in 1964 John Stewart Bell invented a
mathematical formula Bell's inequality
which pointed to a way to experimental
resolve the conflict between Einstein
and ball
most physicists did not pay attention
why bother with the foundational problem
or quantum mechanics that would have no
practical consequences from their
perspective the theory worked it had
been well established in textbooks and
told that Universe the universities for
decade although it was recognized that
quantum entangle entanglement was
inelusive and hard to understand trait
of quantum mechanics
few realized what it should be good for
John clauser also a different opinion
when he heard about Bell's inequality he
became obsessed with how to
experimentally test it he left his main
research Direction and working with the
jungle colleague
named Stuart Friedman managed to perform
the very first experimental test of
balance inequality
they're experimental effort 50 years ago
down on a showstring budget
showed that quantum mechanics violated
by balancing equality and that quantum
mechanics correctly predicted the
outcome of their experiment
sadly negative Bell nor Friedman or is
still with us today
John klauser's experiment appeared
convincing and suggested that Bohr was
more correct than Einstein
but Bell realized that there were few
shortcomings in clauser's experiment
shortcomings that seemed almost
impossible to overcome
it is now that Allen Aspire entered the
scene together with colleagues in France
he managed to overcome these
shortcomings and perform the series of
experiments that were broadly recognized
these experiments were even highlighted
in Swedish newspapers although sometimes
stretched well beyond their actual
results
the experimental test ability inequality
now entered a new era thanks to Anton
seilinger and his collab collaborators
while silinger and others continued to
close some remaining locals in the
closer and Australia experiments even
more importantly they demonstrated how
The elusive concept of quantum
entanglement can be useful
this was a giant leap from tiling as
Austrian predecessor Schrodinger
and it is remarkable how the circle
began in Austria and was closed in
Austria
we have entered a second quantum
Revolution
Professor aspire
Dr klauser and Professor seilinger you
have been awarded a 2022 Nobel Prize in
physics for experiments with entangled
photons establishing the violation of
Bell's inequalities and pioneering
Quantum information science it is an
honor and a privilege to convey to you
on behalf of the royal Swedish Academy
of Sciences our warmest congratulations
may I now please ask you to step forward
and receive your prize from his majesty
decay
first French physicist
to receive his third of this year's
physics prize
[Music]
[Applause]
and then American Laureate John closer
receiving the diploma and the Nobel
medal from his majesty the king
[Music]
[Applause]
and as we heard the loop is closed
Anthony from Austria receives his prize
no
[Applause]
[Music]
for moving on to chemistry some musical
entertainment now Cortez from the petite
Suite by Claude Debussy
[Music]
thank you
foreign
[Music]
thank you
[Applause]
[Music]
foreign
chemistry
by professor uluff romstrom
your majesties your Royal Highness is
esteemed Nobel Prize laureates esteemed
Nobel laureates in 2020 and 2021
distinguished colleagues ladies and
gentlemen
chemistry can be hard sometimes really
hard
and one reason for this is the somewhat
somewhat wild behavior of atoms and
molecules and the complexity of the
environments where they are located
oftentimes the compounds resist many
Brave attempts to tame them to study
them and to use them for our various
purposes
however thanks to our laureates we now
have tools that makes that make this
difficult task easier
instead of tempering the molecules
arduously persuading them to make the
intended connections
which many chemists are indeed very very
good at doing
what about an alternative route
rather than tailoring every specific
connection to perfection
we could use a simpler more
straightforward approach based on very
robust ways to make such connections
such chemistry would be so efficient and
selective that it would work almost
everywhere without complications
this type of connection chemistry does
not come easy
but around the turn of the Millennium
both modern male doll and very sharpless
discovered a very robust chemical
reaction that worked in this very
straightforward way
by allowing an East Side to react with
an alkyne in the presence of copper a
new molecule a so-called triasol was
very efficiently formed
it was as if the two partner molecules
the a side and the alkyne were a perfect
match but needed a little help to find
each other
copper ion then acted as a Matchmaker
and made the two a pair
in a sense it just said click
the sober click
and the two were United
very sharpless called this type of
robust chemistry click chemistry
and the reaction is sometimes called the
click reaction
he envisaged that even rather complex
structures could be assembled with such
reactions
at around the same time Carolyn bertozi
was studying the very very complex world
of glycans
sugar structures often present on Cell
surfaces
to achieve this she developed robust and
very efficient click type chemistry also
based on a sites
that could be performed directly in
living systems
the reactions had to be highly selective
and not interfere with the myriads of
compounds and reactions taking place in
such systems
she called This by orthogonal chemistry
and was able to use this to follow the
fates of the glycans and decipher
intricate biological processes
the achievements and discoveries of our
laureates have had enormous influence on
our society
through the development of inspirational
Concepts and highly efficient methods
the laureates have enhanced our
capabilities and considerably deepened
and widen our knowledge and
understanding
their remarkable chemistry have spurred
intense activity across many different
areas
which has resulted in a wealth of new
highly important accomplishments
Carolyn bertosi Morton male doll Barry
sharpness
you have made groundbreaking discoveries
in chemistry that have led to the
development of Click chemistry and
bioorthogonal chemistry
this is a truly great achievement for
the benefit of humankind
on behalf of the royal Swedish Academy
of Sciences I wish to convey to you our
warmest congratulations
may I now ask you to step forward and
receive your Nobel prizes from the hands
of his majesty the king
first American chemist Carolyn batozzi
who works at Stanford
[Music]
[Applause]
thank you
then Danish chemist Morton meldal
affiliated with the University of
Copenhagen
[Music]
[Applause]
thank you
tearful moment
and finally American chemist Parish
sharpless who was here already in 2001
receiving a Nobel Prize for his work on
Purely catalyzed oxidation reactions
he is now one of the five persons ever
who has received the prize
more than once
[Music]
[Applause]
now some fine music by Edvard Greek we
will be hearing the soul of ice song
from packing
[Music]
foreign
thank you
[Music]
we see
foreign
[Music]
together
foreign
[Music]
[Applause]
thank you
and there the piece is over it's always
song from peregint I composer evergreek
and soloist was a soprano Hana hussar
is it performed by the Royal
Philharmonic
your majesties your Royal highnesses
esteemed Nobel laureates ladies and
gentlemen
who are we and where do we come from
questions such as these have long
intrigued Humanity
everything living leaves traces through
history
ancient Bones have long been studied but
detailed questions on how we are related
cannot be answered in this way
DNA provided new possibilities
DNA holds the code of life
gradual changes to this code form the
basis of evolution and remain in our DNA
as traces from our ancestors
by comparing DNA we can understand
relationships between life forms and
individuals
from an early age was fascinated by
ancient human history
doing studies in Immunology he saw new
possibilities and in secret he studied
Egyptian mummies with the latest DNA
Technologies
his results Drew attention around the
world but challenges were soon obvious
ancient DNA cannot be easily captured
even with the most advanced technology
Pebble therefore embarked on a journey
towards stringency and structure
through deep knowledge on DNA
biochemistry combined with technological
Brilliance persistence passion and
collegiality a new scientific discipline
was born paleo genomics
finally he was ready for his ultimate
Challenge the Genome of our closest
extinct relative the neanderthal
by using new high throughput sequencing
technology and by coordinating an
international Consortium for data
analysis Pebble achieved the seemingly
impossible analysis of the full
Neanderthal genome sequence
Homo sapiens developed in Africa
migrated out and lived side by side with
neanderthals who had adapted to the
Eurasian continent for hundreds of
thousands of years
thanks to parbo's discoveries
fundamental questions could be addressed
and astonishing facts were revealed
Homo sapiens and Neanderthals had
children together and we carry genes
from our extinct relatives that affect
us to this day
influencing for example how we react to
infections
pebu also made The Sensational discovery
of a new hominin by analysis of DNA from
a tiny finger bone
the newly discovered denisova also left
genetic traces that affect us today
svanteperebus discoveries allow us to
address one of the most fundamental
questions of all
what makes us unique
like us neanderthals had big brains they
lived in groups and they used tools but
these changed very little during
hundreds of thousands of years until the
Neanderthals for unclear reasons
disappeared
Homo sapiens on the other hand rapidly
developed complex cultures figurative
art and advanced Innovations
they crossed open Waters and spread to
all parts of our planet
something happened
that gave us new abilities
answers must lie in genetic changes that
occurred after we separated not so long
ago
thanks to pebble's seminal discoveries
genetic variants that are shared among
all now living humans but absent in
neanderthals and beneficials have been
identified
understanding their functional
implications is an exciting Challenge
and a focus of svantependence current
research
and I want to honor the Nobel laureates
from 2020 and 2021
Harvey Alter Michael Houghton and
Charles Rice for the discovery of
hepatitis C virus
David Julius and Arden pataputyan for
their discoveries of receptors for
temperature and touch
your groundbreaking discoveries open the
window to our ancient past
with unexpected implications
the genomes of our closest extinct
relatives provide a novel much more
recent reference points for studies of
who we are and where we came from
it takes more than genetics to
understand what it is to be human
you have provided a solid biological
foundation for further explorations of
this fundamental question
on behalf of the Nobel assembly at
Caroline Sky Institute it is my great
privilege to convey to you our warmest
congratulations
I now ask you to step forward to to
receive the Nobel Prize from the hands
of his majesty the king
to this speech by Professor anavadel
it's time for Swedish laureates
to receive the prize
he's head of the Department of
evolutionary genetics
foreign
[Applause]
Juliet's vaults Arya from Romeo and
Juliet by Char Kuno
[Music]
be here
yes
[Music]
thank you
Christmas
[Music]
[Applause]
thank you
[Music]
[Applause]
foreign
[Music]
[Applause]
foreign
happy French music leading up to the
presentation of the Nobel Prize in
literature
we will hear a speech presentation by
Professor Anderson member of the Swedish
Academy
chairman of the Nobel committee for
literature
foreign
[Music]
ladies and gentlemen
there is a question that increasingly
occupies contemporary literature
what does writing about one's own life
signify
where is the delineation between fiction
and reality
if you have tackled the issue with the
commitment of aniano hello
eternity
she determined early on to rehabilitate
the social class she Rose from
Attack driving her is a force and a
demand for justice but instead of
emulating the poet's language of
imagination to transfigure reality she
chose a different path
foreign language is a means to dispel
the Fogo memory and a knife to uncover
the real
[Music]
in the little Normandy community of give
it to a work of reconstruction it means
has endured in her writing
foreign
it's not but I know soon abandon her
fictional devices
she has said that her debut work could
equally have been called getting rid of
it her maiden name
this is revelatory regarding her
Ambitions
always right autobiographically in a
wider sense setting the ego in a larger
social and historical context in her
most elaborated work the years
it results in what has been called
Collective autobiography and Collective
Britain in the first person
and by her own life story fuses with the
development of French society over six
decades
breakthrough came with a man's place in
1983.
a masterful portrait of a father and a
working-class background that marked him
the book could be written only from the
other side of the class barrier she was
forced to transgress to become the
righteous she is
the language is as received with the
father's simple phrases seemingly
engraved in the strictly factual text
then
whose vision is double aware to what she
has witnessed as a daughter
but also revealing the distance she has
with time accrued
in a woman's story she writes about her
mother in prose as harsh as it is
perceptive as later in lutrophy about
the sister who died young of diphtheria
before Annie knew her and never spoke of
by the parents
then I'm actually it's extraordinary
book written in the form of a letter to
her sister
Bears a strong inner drama wherein erno
tries to reconcile the absence of a
sister
writing is restrained with feelings and
expressions of emotion but passion
pulses beneath the surface
relentlessly
exposes the shame that penetrates class
experience
this occurs in shame where her father's
situation is exposed in scenes that are
as suffused with violence as they are
humility and from another Direction in
her depiction of her illegal abortion at
the age of 23 in happening it's almost
so devastating in its succinctness and
controlled rage
that will be impossible to talk about
that make the Gaze of the other
unbearable
and unrelenting gays and a plain style
or anyone knows characteristics and that
she succeeds in making her pain relevant
to Allah
while asking you to step forward to
receive from the hand of his majesty the
king the queen of Nobel Prize in
literature
[Music]
[Applause]
thank you
okay
foreign
[Music]
[Applause]
thank you
[Music]
[Applause]
foreign
[Music]
music from Finnish composer Ida mubari
to amongst other things was engaging
women's rights
right and now time for the economics
prize
the royal highnesses esteemed laureates
esteemed laureates in economic Sciences
2020 and 2021
ladies and gentlemen
for thousands of years the roofs of fine
castles and churches have been plated
with copper
both the concert hall where we are now
and the City Hall where we shall die in
and dance
have copper rooftops
but before the party starts
please join me on a journey to the Past
we land in Stockholm almost 400 years
ago
in 1624
Sweden is the champion of copper
production
since the government wants a higher
copper price it launches the copper coin
two decades later wanting to raise the
value of copper once more
the government introduces the copper
plate coin
instead of using silver for big payments
the government urges the use of large
minted copper plates
the ten dollar plate weighs almost 20
kilos
it is the bulkiness of the copper
currency that breaks the resistance to
banking
in
1657 Stockholm Banco is open for
business
for the first time Swedish Merchants can
deposit their currency in a bank and
settle payments with a stroke of a pen
no longer need they break their backs
carrying heavy copper plates around the
city
soon the borrowers are even happier than
the depositors
Stockholm's Banco stunt starts to land
at better terms
than Stockholm's traditional money
Landers
but already in 1660 Stockholm Banco
experiences its First Bank Run
the government triggers the run when it
suddenly decides to Mint new lighter
copper plates
since older plates with the same dollar
imprint have a higher copper value
depositors rush to get their old plates
back before someone else does
the bank must halt Landing to the
distress of borrowers seeking to extend
their loans
many of them must sell assets at fire
sale prices
after a second run a few years later
the bank goes under
what to do
can't deposit banks lend liberally
without risking a financial crisis
Sweden's solution is to start a new bank
governed by the parliament
in 1668 with Deep Pockets and at arm's
length from the government
the World's First Central Bank is born
from 1668 let us destroyed
315 years ahead
in 1983 Douglas diamond and Philip divig
developed a fundamental theory of
banking and Bank runs
the theory says that any ideal Financial
arrangement
promises each saver instant access to
her funds yet channels most of these
funds to long-term projects
however
the ideal Arrangement is fragile
just like Stockholm Banco
preventing Bank runs requires public
regulation such as Deposit Insurance and
Emergency Loan facilities
the very same year Ben Bernanke
discovers how bank failures affected the
Great Depression in the 1930s
his analysis of historical records and
economic statistics reveals that bank
failures were costly mainly because of
broken ties between lenders and
Borrowers
not because the money supply fell as we
believed before
their professors Bernanke diamond and
debris
when the great financial crisis hit us
14 years ago your theories were
Vindicated
where the banking system was more robust
and better regulated
the crisis became Milder
recent reforms
bear the imprint of your lessons
just as copper rooftops Shield us from
bad weather
these good laws
will shield us from Financial storms
it is an honor and a privilege for me to
convey to you on behalf of the royal
Swedish Academy of Sciences our warmest
congratulations
may I now please ask you to step forward
and receive your price from his majesty
the king
and his speech was by Professor Tori
Ellingson chairman of the committee for
the price in economic Sciences in memory
of Alfred Nobel
that was actually instituted by the
Swedish Central Bank
in 1968 and first Laureate to receive
this year's economics prize is Ben
Bernanke also known as a former Central
Banker himself
[Music]
foreign
Professor Douglas diamond from
University of Chicago Bull School of
economics
[Applause]
[Music]
and Philip dibig who works and lives in
St Louis United States
one of his favorite pastimes is playing
music
[Applause]
[Music]
and working hard
[Applause]
a proud moment for the three of them I'm
sure
[Applause]
and this was the last prize to be
[Music]
Swedish natural
foreign
[Music]
[Applause]
foreign
[Music]
[Applause]
national anthem the last Musical
piece we will hear is the queen of
sheba's festivity March played while the
guests are leaving the auditorium
[Music]
foreign
thank you